This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions about software
engineering topics at least once a
month. Thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website for
supporting the podcast.
This is Robert for Software Engineering
Radio. I'm at the O'Reilly Strata
Conference in Santa Clara, California.
Jonathan Ellis. Jonathan is the project
chair of the Apache Cassandra project
and the Jonathan and I will be talking
about the Cassandra open source database
project. Jonathan, please tell the
listeners about your background.
My background is
uh
before I started
Cassandra,
I built uh
software like here.
I worked
for a bank.
It looked like a type of app.
That kind
Uh then I I
practiced where I was actually building
a scalable database. And that's how I
got involved
Tell us briefly, what is Cassandra?
Cassandra is a scalable database that
mixes the best of the Google Bigtable
approach and the Amazon Dynamo approach.
Uh specifically we uh Google Bigtable
proposes uh
a log structured storage system that's
highly efficient uh on modern storage
for writes
as well as for uh as well as for reads
and writes
while the Amazon Dynamo system gives the
whole distributed model for uh
replicating uh and partitioning data
with missing computer data. And
Cassandra gives you the best of both
worlds there.
Okay.
us a bit about the history of the
project.
Well, Cassandra was started at Facebook
and open sourced in the summer of 2000
uh 2008
I believe and
I got involved later that year
uh when the project moved to the Apache
Foundation
and we started uh
uh building the community from there and
then the Apache incubator
and uh
graduated in April of last year
and uh we just released our 0.7 version
uh in January.
Why are people now looking at
alternatives to relational databases?
It's mostly because
uh I Well, there's a couple reasons. You
have this this whole NoSQL general
uh term for anything that's not a
relational database. And there's there's
all kinds of of systems under that
rubric. Uh but I think I think the
really interesting problem is is the one
of scale that relational databases
weren't designed to scale and don't do
it particularly well. And uh in fact, if
you can you can make a relational system
scale by partitioning it and uh you
know, adding enough duct tape and
bailing wire, but what you end up with
is uh it's two things. There's one it
it's it's very ad hoc and one-off. ish
Uh you you can't take uh
an architecture that partitions a
relational database for you know, eBay
and and run you know, Amazon's
infrastructure on top of that even
though they're both you know, e-commerce
sites.
Uh
The other is is that when you do this,
when you when you take a relational
system and you partition it and you make
it scale, you're giving up you you you
have to give up the benefits that
make you want to choose a relational
system in the first place, you know,
your your acid guarantees.
So, uh
you know, companies that are running
into, you know, these these big data
problems are are taking a look at this
and saying, you know, either we can
build a one-off uh that doesn't doesn't
really take advantage of uh the
strengths of the relational platform, or
I can go with a system that's designed
for this kind of new breed of
application, and and uh gives me some
some benefits to make up for giving up
acid.
People are are trying to rethink the
problem in a more fundamental way, and
not just get stuck with certain
trade-offs you get by trying to fit the
round peg in a square hole.
Yeah, I I think so. I think that more
and more companies are running into, you
know, data sets and query volumes that
can't be handled by single-machine
databases anymore. And uh and once you
start partitioning, then then these
these
uh scalable database like Cassandra is
going to be a better fit for your
application.
Would you accept the division into the
non-relational stores into key-value
stores, document-oriented, and big table
type column family?
Uh yeah, I think I wrote uh I wrote an
article a couple years ago called the
NoSQL Ecosystem, and
uh
you know, one of the things I talked
about there is that there's several
different axes on which to evaluate uh a
database. You know, one of them is the
data model.
You know, that's that's what you're
talking about here with document versus
key-value versus column family.
But, there there's other important
factors to to keep in mind when
evaluating these systems. Uh one of one
of which is uh not only what's the data
model, but what's the storage model,
which are related uh but not the same
thing. Uh for instance,
uh
there's a a database called Riak by
company named Basho.
And it gives you a document data model,
but it's implemented
uh in terms of uh pluggable key-value
systems. So, uh you can, you know, run
it on top of uh BigTable or on top of uh
Bitcask, which is uh a a new key-value
single-machine database that they wrote
to it to back Riak. Um so, so there's
uh
you know, very different characteristics
depending on the the implementation
there.
Uh
All right, in the same vein, you have uh
CouchDB. Also gives you a document data
model, but that's implemented in terms
of append-only B-trees. So, the
performance characteristics of uh
you know, Bitcask versus uh CouchDB
versus uh MongoDB, you know, are quite
different.
Let's talk about the data model of
Cassandra. Give us an overview of the
main concepts in the data model.
So, Cassandra uh takes the uh data model
primarily from uh Google BigTable and
divides the world up into uh key spaces
and column families, which correspond to
schemas and tables in a relational
database. And the the difference between
a column family and a table
uh is that Well, there's a couple of
differences. One is that
uh
that columns in your rows in a Cassandra
column family are sort of uh
you know, it's not it's not schema-less
because you can annotate columns and
say, "This column will be of this type,
and I want you to enforce that for me."
Uh but, it's uh
it's a it's a sparse model because you
can have
uh you can use columns in your rows
without pre-declaring them if you want
to. And then you can later add the
metadata about the data tap type or or
you can just leave it as as a as a
column full of bytes and and Cassandra
Cassandra's okay with that.
Uh so so one of the differences is then
that
you don't have to
uh
reallocate each row in your table to add
a column. So you you can think of either
alter table as being optional or you can
think of it as much higher performance
uh than than what you would have in a in
a B-tree based system. And either of
those ways of thinking about it is
correct.
You uh have made a distinction between
more of a static schema, although it's
not really enforced by the server,
versus more of a dynamic schema where
you freely add columns.
Sure. Yeah, so I I like to think of
modeling applications in Cassandra in
terms of two sort of classes of column
family
uh that I would I call static and
dynamic column families. And I I'm I'm
using static and dynamic in kind of the
sense of uh
how much change is going on at runtime
rather than in in the sense of
uh you know, static versus dynamic
typing or something. So in other words,
a static column family would be a column
family that you know, the rows are
representing objects uh in your
application for instance. So they all
have more or less the same columns. Uh
you may you may you know, six months
into deploying your website uh decide
that you're going to have users provide
you with an SMS number as well as an
email address to contact them. And so
you can just you you, know, by not
having to do an alter table, your
application can just start putting in
that SMS number without having to do any
extra work on the, uh,
you know, on the DBA side. Uh, but, you
know, you still have most of most of
your rows, you know, share the same set
of columns just by convention. Uh, then
the other way, the other kind of column
family is is where we,
uh, use a column family to represent,
uh,
you know, materialized views in a single
row. And
uh, this this is where when we did our
0.7 release, one of the things that a
lot of, uh, news stories picked up on
was that, uh, Cassandra 0.7 can now have
up to 2 billion columns in a single row.
Uh, you know,
the old limitation was you can have up
to 2 GB worth of data in a single row,
uh, because we were representing, you
know, the size field on disk as as a
32-bit, uh, integer.
Uh,
and so now it now the now the limit has
has become the number of columns is is 2
billion. And then the size is basically
limited by your disk space.
Uh,
so the but so either way we're talking
about really large numbers of columns
compared to what you would have in a
relational system. And the reason is is
that, uh, it's not because we're insane,
but it's because we're we're
we're providing you with a tool to avoid
joins.
Because, uh, you know, even in even in a
relational system,
uh,
you know, people learn to avoid joins,
for you know, maximum performance.
Uh, but, you know, that's even more
important in a distributed system where
rows in different tables or different
column families could live on different
machines altogether. And so the price of
doing the expensiveness of doing that
join goes up even further because you're
dealing with network latency is
and not just data that's all local to a
single machine. So so we really want to
emphasize avoiding joins and and having
the ability to put you know
millions or billions of columns in a
single row lets us denormalize
your query result set and precompute it
into one of these rows.
You know, for for instance
uh
one of one of the sort of teaching
examples we have of doing Cassandra uh
you know
development is a toy Twitter clone
called Twissandra. So if you go to
twissandra.com,
there's a there's a live demo and
there's a link to the GitHub source and
it it's written in Python on top of
Django but it it's it's it's
one of the nice things about Python is
it's quite readable even if you don't
really have a Python background. Uh so
so it's it's a pretty good example even
if you're a Java programmer or Pearl
programmer or whatever.
Uh but one of the things the core the
core query you make in Twitter is
you know, what tweets
have my friends made?
And so the the way you would model this
in a relational database is you would
have a table for tweets and a table for
users and a table
to relate users to other users to say
who are my friends. And then you would
if you want to say give me the 50 most
recent tweets that my friends have made
uh then you know, what what you're doing
is you you first you have to say well,
what is the set of tweets my friends
have made and I compute that by by going
through these joint tables and then I I
can pull out those tweet rows, sort them
by time and give you back the result.
It's a pretty simple design problem for
anyone who's
read a book about relational databases
using a normalized model. So, how would
you do that with Cassandra to take
advantage of Cassandra's data models?
So, the the the way you would
uh do that in Cassandra is I would have
uh a single row I would have a separate
column family that would be you know
where I answer this query from of what
tweets of my friends made.
Uh and Cassandra calls that the timeline
column family.
And so, I would have a row in that
column family for each user.
And the columns in that row are going to
be the tweets.
I I will denormalize each tweet that
someone makes into uh the timeline row
of the people who follow him.
In the relational model, the idea you
normalize everything every piece of data
is in one place. You can always find the
data you want if you're willing to do
enough joins.
Whereas with Cassandra, it sounds like
what you do is think about the queries
that you're going to do and then
create one storage
class for each tweet each query.
Right. That's exactly right. And you
know you there's
uh you know you you
What what we typically see at uh at
DataStax when people come to us and say,
"Hey, you know we're writing this
application against uh Cassandra. Can
you review our data model?" is uh
you know because Cassandra does give you
this rows and columns uh
sort of uh
uh
view of the world, uh they'll treat it
like a slightly brain damaged uh
relational database. And they and
they'll uh do you know all their joins
uh client side. And and and and still
have this sort of normalized uh data
model only in Cassandra.
And that's that's you know
Cassandra tries to push you away from
that into into this denormalized model
you know to save you from yourself
because that that's that's how you're
going to get uh
you know really good performance and and
having basically best in class right
performance lets us say hey you know
creating those extra copies you know
isn't as expensive as you're used to
thinking it as. So go ahead and and and
spend some
uh rights you know at at uh creation
time to precompute those queries so that
they're lightning fast.
Suppose you're dealing with an
application that has a bunch of
different relations and there's many
different queries
come
first through A to B to C and then B to
C to A and so on and you you end up
having 20 different queries.
Is this a efficient way
or people having success in building
applications with dozens of different
copies of the same data
based on the number of ways they need to
access it or is that just the wrong
application for this data store?
Uh
so
well there there's there's an important
thing that that I haven't mentioned
which is that while Cassandra doesn't
support joins it does support indexes.
So uh this is something that you know
certainly the the the key value
uh type of databases you know they don't
give you that uh kind of uh
you know more sophisticated query
capability and Cassandra does. So uh
you know
that that does that helps a lot where
this with with this kind of application
where you're saying that you know I
I have a lot of different combinations
of of uh you know things I need to ask
and and maybe you know precomputing them
all is combinatorially
uh impractical. So, having those having
those indexes that that allow Cassandra
to
you know
apply
predicates to your query at runtime
can can help with a lot of those
situations.
Now, that said,
you know, if you have something that's
you know
truly
ad hoc queries at runtime, you know,
that's that's really
a super hard problem to scale
and the lack of joins makes it harder in
one respect in Cassandra,
but any system that's going to give you
joins is going to give you a different
set of problems. So, I would say that
Cassandra's probably about as good as
anything else when you have that
combination of I need to be able to do
those queries, but I also need to scale.
I'd like to get more into the systems
side of the project. From reading the
paper reading a paper from two Facebook
guys about Cassandra, they said the
major properties of Cassandra are
distributed
decentralized, scalable, highly
available, fault tolerant and tunable
consistency. Would you agree with that
list?
Yeah, I'd say that I'd say that's still
accurate. I'd maybe I'd maybe add high
performance.
Let's talk about how how does Cassandra
achieve
distribution?
There's a couple things that that kind
of fall under the distribution category.
One is
you know, how do I
spread data across multiple machines and
the other is you know, how do I you
know, now that I have my data spread
across multiple machines, how do I make
sure that I have multiple copies of it
as well. So, the the first that that
first part we call partitioning and the
second part we call replication.
And
both of those are
pluggable
uh
you know, strategies in Cassandra. Uh
and most commonly uh the partitioning is
done by a uh consistent hashing
partitioner uh called random partitioner
and that that uh
basically that that distributes
uh rows around the cluster by uh the MD5
of their primary key.
Now, replication is a little more uh
interesting because there's so many
different uh you know, things you can
want to achieve with it. For instance,
you might want to say I I want I want
three copies of my data, but I want to
guarantee that there's at least one copy
in each of two data centers.
Or you might want to say that, you know,
I have uh
you know, three sets of data and I want
all of them to live in
uh
each of one data center, but then I want
a master copy of each of those pieces of
each of those sets of data in a port.
So, you see the multi-data center
deployment at simply uh
one of the possible conditions you face
in distributing your data. It's not a
separate
engineering task. Now, we've got the
data center up and running. How do we
solve multiple data centers?
Right. And and this this comes out of
Cassandra's design as uh a fully
distributed system. There's no special
nodes in a Cassandra cluster.
Uh and so, what you see in in a lot of
older systems, older designs, is that
there will be some kind of master that
uh you know,
is responsible for a certain range of
data. And uh you know, writes will be
fast as long as you're in the same data
center as that master. But then uh you
know, you
you know, if you want to replicate to
another data center, then you can't you
can't do writes in that data center. You
have to send them over to the master.
And then maybe we replicate to the
second by log shipping or something like
that. So, it's kind of you know you
know, a second system grafted on to the
original uh single data center design.
Whereas with uh Cassandra
uh you know, a
a second data center is just you know,
um more nodes in the cluster that happen
to be across uh a high latency link.
And so, Cass- Cassandra, you know
replication by and large, everything
works exactly the same as in a single
data center with the exception that
Cassandra recognizes that you know, hey,
that that
gap that that you know, that WAN link is
higher latency and more expensive. So,
what I'm going to do is if if I need to
uh replicate to multiple nodes that are
in that other data center, then what
I'll do is I'll send that right to a
single node with a node that says also
forward it to this other node that's
local to you, so that I so that I
minimize my use of that uh expensive
link.
Is do people typically think in terms of
one data center being live and the other
being a backup or do you see the entire
Cassandra cluster as being simply spread
over a wide geographic area and you
don't really care where in that cluster
you write to?
Mostly you know, peop- people find that
you know, having that ability to have a
multi-master system across data data
centers uh is really useful uh because
that allows you to have if you have if
you're serving users on the East Coast
and the West Coast or uh you know, in
California and in Europe uh you can have
those clients do their updates to you
know, the nodes that are closest to
them. And uh uh
so it it it and you get you kind of get
the geographic redundancy for free, but
maybe the the lower latency to your
clients is maybe the more important of
those two qualities.
Walk us through what happens on a right.
So on a on a right, Cassandra's So you
you can talk to any node in a Cassandra
cluster and give it a right and it will
take care of sending it to the right
replicas. So this this is uh
Could I interrupt you there? A client it
can connect to any node in the cluster.
There's
Right.
And do you typically use a load balancer
or how how does the client find
which node to connect to?
There's kind of no wrong answer there.
Uh there's there's a bunch of ways you
can do it. My favorite is to use round
robin DNS, but uh you know, we we do see
deployments using load balancers like
HAProxy or uh hardware load balancers or
even a more kind of uh client side
approach by
uh you know, clients like Hector for
Java uh support you give it a you know,
any Cassandra node and it will ask that
Cassandra node, "Hey, tell me about the
other nodes in the cluster." And then uh
then the client will spread its
connections around all of all of those
uh
uh nodes or or the ones that are local
to it in the same data center.
So uh
you know, Cassandra also supports uh
uh
a smart API called the storage proxy
API, where the client actually routes
the data directly to the right replicas.
Uh we we deemphasize that a little bit
because that's that's a Java only.
Uh but it it is out there
uh for people who want to use it. We do
have
uh you know at least a handful of
production deployments using that. But
the by and large
most most deployments use the Thrift API
and use something like Hector
on top of that in Java or Picasso in
Python and so forth. So when
the node that a client connects to
is called the coordinator node.
And that's that will be responsible for
sending
the right out to the right replicas and
then reporting back to the client
success or failure based on what it gets
back from those replicas.
So you know
success or failure is is a little bit of
a fuzzy concept in Cassandra because we
support
tunable consistency levels. Meaning
you can tell Cassandra
consider this right a success only if
it's written to the majority of replicas
for that row.
Or you could require just a single
replica to be available to consider that
right a success and accept that it will
have to be replicated to the others that
are down right now or unreachable
at a future point.
Does a client control the number of
replicas on a right per operation or do
you set that per column family or
cluster?
Yes. So in other words there's there's
two factors for the number of replicas.
There's the total number of replicas of
a row and that's that's set
per key space.
How many total replicas you want of of
data in that set of column family.
But the number number of replicas
we block for before calling the right a
success is per operation.
You have two numbers there. The total
number of replicas that will eventually
be written and the number that you need
for a client to uh a client operation to
return.
Right.
Okay.
Now, walk us through what happens on a
read.
A read a read uh gets a little bit more
complicated. Uh so, you know, at the at
the high level, it's it's like a write
only, you know, the other direction. A
client talks to a coordinator, says, "I
want you know, I want some set of
columns from this row." Uh and the
coordinator goes out and gets it. You
know, drilling down a little further,
though,
things get a little more complicated.
Because uh
you know, we want we want to be
efficient. In other words, if I have
five copies of a piece of data and
uh I have for every request, I'm pulling
all of those five copies back, uh you
know, that that's that's using up a lot
of of network traffic.
I don't want to do that.
So, well, what Cassandra does, what the
coordinator does,
is it says, uh well, first of all, it
says, "How many uh
uh requests how Well, what consistency
level am I operating at? How many
replies do I need to compare to to uh
call this read uh successful and and
make sure I'm giving the client, you
know, as as
fresh a copy of the data as it as it's
requesting."
Uh and once once it uh calculates that,
it will go through Cassandra has a
subsystem called the failure detector
that uh it uses
uh
uh an algorithm uh that's described in a
paper called the five failure detector.
And uh in it it's a very sophisticated
probabilistic uh
failure detection algorithm based on uh
gossip heartbeat. Uh so, so we can say
with with high accuracy, you know, if if
I haven't received a heartbeat from this
node for a few seconds,
uh and network traffic has been volatile
recently, then, you know, he's probably
still alive. It's probably just another
network hiccup.
Uh but, you know, the longer it goes,
the more likely it is that he's
actually, you know, really experiencing
downtime or a long-lived partition. So
so I I get this list of node uh of
replicas that are uh
that are not failed. And then I take the
uh closest one.
Uh and and how we determine closeness
uh is is a a separate
uh subject we can go into. But, I take
the closest one, and I say, "I want you
to send me the data in the columns that
are being requested." And the other the
other replicas that I need to satisfy
the consistency level, I will send them
just a request for a hash of those
columns. So that, you know, I'm I'm only
uh sending the full body of the of the
result set once.
So it's an optimistic system because
most of the time those digests are going
to match the body, in which case I just
say, "Okay, client, here's here's your
result." Uh
uh but but if there's a failure, if
there's a digest mismatch of those hash
hashes, then I have to go and do with a
second round, and I say, "Okay, this
time I'm going to ask for the full body
uh of the result set from everyone, so I
can figure out where the you know, who's
got stale data, and send him a more
recent uh copy."
We know from the CAP theorem that data
stores either fall into the category
that emphasize or distributed data
stores either emphasize consistency more
availability. Would it be fair to say
then that Cassandra is trading off more
toward availability?
And it's willing to give you uh data
that might be a little bit out of date
in order to give you something.
Cassandra gets put into that category
most often.
Uh
but it's it's more
Cassandra lets you choose which one you
want. You know, if if I uh ask for
quorum consistency level on rights and
quorum consistency level on reads, then
my readers will always see the most
recently written values. So, so we'll be
a consistent uh system.
But uh you know, that means that I can
only if I have a three uh
node replication factor, then quorum
consistency will only let me lose a
single uh
node before I have to say
uh I can't fulfill these requests
anymore because the system is you know,
too damaged. That I've lost too many
machines. So, often you know,
uh
production deployments will say, you
know, I am okay with seeing
uh stale data uh during failure
conditions. So, I I'm going to reduce
the the consistency level I require
to get that higher availability.
What happens when you add a node to the
cluster?
Uh when you add a node to the cluster,
then
uh the existing nodes
stream over
uh the data that the new node is
becoming responsible for. So, uh part of
part of uh using something like
consistent hashing and and getting
uh you know,
constant time routing with no uh central
master is that uh
we we have we do have to move that data
to the new one that you know, its
position in the token ring indicates
that it should be responsible for. So,
uh we we call that bootstrapping uh the
process of of moving data to uh a new
node in the system. Uh the good news is
is that because we manage our own data
on disk, uh we can do that without
imposing any random IO on the system.
It's all just sequential reads uh from
the existing machines and sequential
writes uh on the new node. And so it so
it's actually
uh
you know, it's over very quickly and uh
and very efficient.
How big are some of the clusters that
you're seeing your clients use at
DataStax?
The biggest one that I know of is uh
cluster running Digital Reasoning
software for the US government that's
over 400 nodes. Uh
there's a lot of clusters. That's a
That's sort of the you know, that the
outlier on the size scale.
The
the uh
the mean
uh or the mode cluster size and the most
common cluster size is probably between
20 and 40 nodes. Uh and we do have it at
the other end of the spectrum. We We
have one client that's running just uh
they they started with just two nodes uh
because you know, they knew they wanted
to scale and that uh
you know, Cassandra would be able to do
that seamlessly
uh and they didn't they didn't have to
start with a huge cluster to begin with.
And is each node in the cluster then
running the Phi failure detection
algorithm?
Yes.
And then uh
if a node goes down, then other nodes
would fairly quickly identify it as down
using this algorithm?
Mhm.
And do they go through a reverse of the
node addition process to create enough
replicas for data that was on the failed
node?
That's a good question because what we
actually do is we don't assume that a
node is dead permanently until a human
intervenes and says, "Okay, he's not
coming back." Because the most common
failure condition is some kind of
temporary failure, whether
uh whether it's a switch that failed and
so the node's unreachable or a circuit
was overloaded and the node goes down,
but you know, all the data is still
there. Uh
having a node that's absolutely wiped
out and the data doesn't exist anymore
is relatively rare. So, we don't we
don't want to impose the overhead of uh
you know, rebuilding that data uh
you know, until until someone says that
it is necessary. Uh
And that's that's the nice thing about
having
uh you know, you know, a replication
factor that's you know, basically as
high as you want, but the com- the most
common one is is replication factor
three because you know, if you just have
a single replica,
uh well, there's a couple drawbacks of
that. You know, one is that uh a quorum
of two is still two. So, so you don't
have if you're doing quorum consistency,
you can't lose anything before you have
to start uh denying requests. But the
other is that uh from a you know, I
don't want to lose my data point of
view, if I have two replicas and one of
them goes down, then I'm I'm really
really nervous uh until I can
re-replicate it because now, you know,
when one's down, I just have a single
copy and if I lose that, then game over.
Uh but if you have a replication factor
three, then you know, even if I lose one
uh one copy, you know, I'm I'm still
feeling confident because I still have
two copies and uh
you know, I don't start to get nervous
again until you know, I and unless I
lose a second one before the first one
comes back online or gets re-replicated.
What about the case where you have two
data centers and you lose a data center
or they lose communication? You've
configured it to put one replica in the
other data center then at that point
would you want the
uh if you think you've lost a data
center for a while, would you want the
surviving data center to
re-replicate data so you have your
desired number of copies within that
data center?
Usually usually not because again, you
know, if I lose the entire data center
then uh
it's probably
uh you know, some kind of network
problem and that that that data center
will be back online uh
within
probably hours, worst case probably
days.
Uh
and so, you know, you you replicate uh
in Cassandra
uh to you know, to protect your data not
to not not to improve performance. Uh
so, maybe that you know, people coming
from a relational database background,
you may be thinking, well, you know,
I'll I'll create more replicas to handle
more traffic.
But uh the the the right way to handle
more traffic in Cassandra is to add more
machines and spread your uh data across
more machines rather than increasing the
the replication count which would you
know, just put more copies across the
same number of machines. And because
remember that you know, we're we're
doing that comparing of digests uh of of
uh of the different replicas uh with
with uh the data on each read. So uh
and
so in general unless there's some some
caveats you can turn off read repair for
instance. But in you know, in the out of
the box configuration, you don't add
more capacity by adding replicas. Uh
you you
you add more capacity by adding more
machines and spreading those replicas
more thinly across those machines.
You just mentioned read repair. Tell us
how that works.
So, read repair means that even if I say
even if if I do a read at consistency
level one, which means which says you
know, just give me you know, the result
from the
the closest replica,
Cassandra will in the background
go ahead and after it gives you that
reply, it will go and ask the other
replicas for digests of what it just
read so it can make sure that they are
up to date. So, that's one of the three
ways that Cassandra keeps its
replication
in sync. So, there's there's
there's no way to to break Cassandra's
replication such that it has to rebuild
from scratch,
which is which is a really nice
property.
Uh
You know, coming from a relational
background,
I I
you know, I've seen a slow knee
replication for PostgreSQL. You know,
just you know, the only way to
to make it recover what was to rebuild
the slave from scratch.
You really don't want to have to do that
in a production environment.
No, and no because not only is it
does it impose a very large
performance penalty while you're doing
that. You know, it also means that
you're in that situation where now I
just have that one copy of my data and
I'm nervous.
You know, if something goes wrong while
I'm rebuilding, I'm I'm not in a happy
place.
So, the the three ways that Cassandra
uses to to keep its replication up to
date
are read repair that we mentioned,
hinted handoff, and anti-entropy repair.
And all of all of those terms come from
the Amazon Dynamo paper and they're a
little they they don't mean anything to
you unless you've read that paper. So,
uh briefly, uh what those other two
mean, hinted handoff means that uh if
I'm doing a write
and the failure detector lets me know,
"Hey, you know, this this
replica of this write is down." Uh
then
uh if well, it I'll then one of two
things will happen. If I don't have
enough replicas alive to satisfy by the
consistency level, then I'll tell the
client, uh you know, I'll I'll give it
an unavailable exception that says, you
know, "There aren't enough live replicas
to satisfy your request."
Uh but but if I do have enough live
replicas to satisfy the request, then I
will send one of the live ones
uh a piece of metadata with the write
that says, "Replay this write uh to this
this this replica of that that's down
right now. When he comes back up, replay
it." So, that that's called that's
called the hint, and and the replay
process is called handoff. So, that
that's where that that's where that term
comes from.
Uh then the the third
uh
way to achieve consistency is the
anti-entropy repair. And that's uh
basically uh you know, it's basically
rsync for databases. So, what we're
going to do is uh we're going to build a
tree of hashes
uh for each range of data in the in the
replica.
And uh we exchange those hash trees in
such a way that uh we we find out which
data blocks are out of sync
in logarithmic time. And we're only
exchanging those hashes over the network
until we we find what is actually out of
sync, and then we then we uh repair
that.
So, you efficiently compare trees
without having to send the the trees
back and
Yeah, I mean, worst you will send the
entire tree back and forth, but you
know, that that would be the case of I
you know, I rm-rf my data directories
and nothing's there anymore.
Uh
when when there is data that that's
shared between them, even if it's only a
little bit, then uh Cassandra will will
be able to avoid replicating
uh that part.
I'd like to switch gears and talk about
the storage model you mentioned very
early on in the interview. Plus,
uh give us an overview of the storage
model that Cassandra uses.
So, so far we've been talking about in
terms of replication and consistency
level of uh Cassandra's kind of Dynamo
heritage. And then moving to the storage
model, then we were kind of switching
gears to
uh you know, the the BigTable influence.
And so, actually BigTable actually
wasn't uh
uh first to describe
uh this kind of storage model, which is
uh
a log-structured storage model for
databases. Uh that comes from a paper in
1996 called the log-structured merge
tree.
And uh that that paper didn't get a
whole lot of attention until Google
cited it
uh in BigTable uh 10 years later. But,
what uh what happens
you know, at the storage layer when a
replica when a write comes into a
replica uh that belongs on that node is
uh
you know, it's so
you know, you know, most uh
most databases use a a B-tree based
storage model that's more or less
update-in-place.
Uh you know, there's there's uh
uh you know, there's a little bit of a
wrinkle from things like multi-version
concurrency control, but you you can
pretty much think of it as as an
update-in-place storage model where you
know, there's a certain uh block of data
that a row lives in, and then we follow
an index down to find block, and then we
update the columns uh uh for
uh for an update request.
Now, in Cassandra, what we do instead is
uh when we have updates come in for a
column family, we put them in a
structure called a memtable.
And we that we we collect we collect
updates, and we don't we don't uh turn
those into a file on disk until the
memtable is full.
And then we we sort the memtable by row,
and then we write it out uh
to disk, where we call it an SSTable.
You know, it's a it's a data file. And
once it's written on disk,
it's immutable. We never do update in
place. Uh
we we only we we update by putting a new
version in a new memtable, and
eventually writing that out to a new
data file.
Does the node serve writes or reads and
writes out of the memtable?
Yes, so the data in the memtable is live
for read requests immediately. And what
we'll do is if if uh
you know, if I have a row for my user
record
uh on on a website, and uh so you know,
my company changed its name recently
from Riptano to DataStax. So, in my
profile, I have my URL, it says
riptano.com. And then I come in and say,
"Hey, no, I changed my company name, so
I'm going to change my URL to
datastax.com."
Well, I have my original uh
uh record on disk in an SSTable file.
Now, I have my new URL in a memtable
uh that hasn't been written to disk yet.
So, if someone comes in and says,
uh you know, the equivalent of select
star from users where uh username is
jbls,
then I will you know, Cassandra will
merge that new value that's sitting in
the memtable with the row that's on
disk, and say, you know, this new value
supersedes the one that was in the row
on disk. The rest of the data that was
on disk is still current, so I'll I'll
I'll present that in the result set as
is.
Does a write complete successfully
before anything's been written to disk?
Short short answer is no, because before
we put the
data in the memtable, we append it to a
commit log.
So this is the same kind of
architecture that
traditional databases use to provide
durability is we append to commit log
and then
the
the tunable
parameter here is how often do we fsync
that commit log? In other words, how
often do we tell the operating system to
actually send that data in the commit
log to disk? And so if if you have your
commit log on a separate device than the
data files that you're doing reads from,
then you know, you're just constantly
doing appends. That's a very
that's a very fast operation because I'm
not having to seek the disk head around.
But
And and so this is the same for
relational databases as for Cassandra or
at least commit log oriented relational
databases
that that you want to have that on that
on that separate device and performance
is worse if it's not. Now
there's kind of a workaround
for you know, having it
you know, on a non-performing
environment which is that we're we'll
only fsync every so many seconds.
Instead of instead of uh
grouping up writes into into groups of
say uh
you know uh
10 milliseconds worth of writes and and
fsyncing those together or 1 millisecond
worth of rights and F syncing those
together.
Uh we will
uh
because you know, even if it's on it's
on device, you don't want to F sync for
each individual
uh right. You want to batch those up
somehow. Uh but we can relax that and
say we're we'll only F sync you know,
every 10 seconds uh no matter how many
rights come in to give you better
performance. You have to have your
commit log on a shared disk with your
data files.
What you're trying to do here then is
support a lot of rights without having
to do a lot of seeks on the spindle.
Exactly.
Are there clients for all the popular
programming languages?
Well, I guess that depends on uh what
you call popular. Uh
there's there's two levels to the to the
client story in Cassandra. There's
there's uh
you know, the the raw communication
protocol is an RPC framework. Uh RPC and
serialization called Thrift.
Uh and that
you know, generates code for
uh you know, around a dozen languages.
Uh
and
and yeah, I I think that does cover
pretty much all the popular ones.
Uh
actually one the the only one that I've
had someone request a client for that
that Thrift doesn't handle is Delphi.
So, that but you know, C# uh Erlang
OCaml uh Smalltalk uh
uh
Java, Pearl, Ruby, Python.
Yeah, I mean, you know, and you know,
even some fairly obscure ones like those
others, you know, Thrift does support.
But then, Thrift is really the right way
to think about Thrift is that it's kind
of the driver. So, sort of like libpq
for PostgreSQL. You you you you you
you don't really want to write your
application code with Thrift RPC calls
if you can possibly help it. And so,
that that's where it's it's a little
more sparse. We have clients for
Java, for Python, for Ruby, for PHP, and
those are the ones that are that are
really well supported.
Oh, C# as well.
But, C++ is uh
a little more touchy. Uh there's there's
a uh client out there that that
needs a little bit of fleshing out to be
a really full-fledged uh
uh environment. Uh Pearl
uh is another one where uh there
there isn't a really good
uh client that's up to date for the
Cassandra 0.7 features.
Those are Those are the two main ones
that we'd like to see, I think uh
uh
a little bit of story with those uh C++
and Pearl.
Does Cassandra support anything like
transactions?
It supports something like transactions,
but not transactional per se. So, when
we think of transactions, we think of,
you know, the atomic, isolated,
consistent, and durable. Uh well,
Cassandra gives you durable.
And if it wasn't clear uh in my
description earlier, you absolutely can
configure Cassandra so that uh uh every
write is 100% durable even if you lose
power.
Uh every write that was acknowledged
will be there when you come back up. Uh
so, we do durability. And we we do
atomicity
with within limits. Uh so, atomicity
means that, you know, if I give you a
write, either all of it will happen or
none of it. Uh and Cassandra gives you
atomicity within a single row.
Uh that that's the uh that's the level
of of what we put in a commit log, and
the level of and that's the level of uh
uh routing of of uh data and
partitioning.
But, you know,
more broadly, when people think of
transactions, they say, "Well, you know,
I want updates to these different
tables, and I want I want all of those
to, you know,
happen as a group." And so, Cassandra
doesn't give you
atomicity across multiple different
rows.
Uh but, what it does give you is this
concept called a batch. So, that's sort
of the That's That's the thing that's
like a transaction to Cassandra. is you
can have a batch of updates, and you
send it off to Cassandra. And if, you
know, what you need to worry about is
the coordinator node
failing partway through. That's That's
the edge case there.
Uh if the coordinator node fails partway
through, then
the client needs to fail over to another
uh
node to talk to a new coordinator.
And And that's one of the things that
good clients handle for you, like, you
know, Hector and Pycassa. Uh you know,
they're going to handle that for you.
And then you retry the batch.
And And the property of the batches is
that, you know, even if part of it got
applied already,
retrying it uh will be item potent. And
And And uh only the, you know, the parts
that weren't applied will happen, and
the parts that already did, you know, no
harm done. We're We're We're still cool.
If you're designing a highly normalized
highly denormalized database, or there's
multiple copies of the same data for
different queries,
you could have batches that are
partially completed. Then isn't it the
case that clients would have to be
prepared to deal with what we would call
referential integrity failures during
reads?
You You have to worry about that if
you're not fully denormalized. If you're
only partially denormalized, then you
have to worry about that because, you
know, partially denormalized means I'm
doing some kind of joins
uh client side. And And that's where you
have to worry about that. If you're
fully denormalized such that, you know,
each query is coming from one of these
materialized view rows, then, you know,
the data in that row, you know, because,
you know, I said data within a row is
atomic, you don't have to worry about
that.
Okay, got it. So, it either succeeds or
it doesn't, but it's
If we could proceed to talk a little bit
about the project,
tell us about the structure of Cassandra
as an open-source project.
Well, Cassandra's really uh it's a great
open-source success story. You know, I
mentioned that I started working on
Cassandra while I was at Rackspace. Uh
you know, we we started getting
engineers from Dig and Twitter working
on it. Today, we have substantially over
100 uh people who contributed at least
one patch, and more who contributed bug
reports and so forth. You know,
Rackspace, you know, for instance,
wasn't looking to build something
solo.
It it's it's really been, you know,
today,
uh you know, DataStax has
quite a few people on it full-time, but
it it it's still
uh it's still a very healthy community
where,
uh you know, it's developed in the open,
and people from different companies are
working on it together. Uh and it it's
it's one of the healthiest uh
communities in that respect that I that
I uh seen that.
Do you have mailing lists,
wiki, forum, things like that?
Yeah, we Yeah, there's there's uh a user
mailing list, a developer mailing list,
a client developer mailing list.
Uh
a lot of the action
You you kind of seen this in the in the
open-source world in general in the last
few years is uh you know, projects have
moved a little bit more towards
real-time communication.
Uh and so,
younger projects, uh I think I think
there's a common trend towards
emphasizing something like IRC a little
bit more than mailing lists. Uh and we
have we we do a lot of our
uh development in the Cassandra dev
channel on Freenode. And uh there's
there's a just pound Cassandra channel
for users there that consistently has
about a couple hundred people there. And
uh basically pretty much any time zone
you're in you can get uh
get uh real-time help uh
in IRC. And you know, there's there's
there's also the mailing list for more
involved discussions or more
uh you know,
more high latency, I guess.
If people want to find out more about
the project, where should they go?
I they should go to uh apache.
uh cassand- sorry, other way around.
cassandra.apache.org.
Uh and I would I would particularly
recommend the wiki page
uh called articles and presentations.
And uh that that has uh
um several high-quality
uh
you know, articles uh about Cassandra
uh at the top of the page.
Tell us about your company, DataStax.
So, I started uh DataStax uh about 8
months ago. We called it Riptano and we
recently changed our name. And uh we we
provide
uh professional products and support for
Cassandra. We have over 50
uh support uh customers. And uh then you
know, then there's the customers that
we've done uh
product design and training with. It's
uh it's going really well.
Uh this week at Strata we're we're
introducing our Cassandra management uh
platform called OpsCenter.
And uh and starting to give that out to
uh
you know, interested beta users.
Do you personally write or blog
anywhere?
I do most of my blogging these days on
the DataStax website. Uh so, DataStax I
think it's datastax.com/blog,
but it's definitely linked uh from the
main site. And I'm I'm uh spiced on
Twitter as p y c e d uh for sort of
obscure historical reasons.
We will have a link to that and all the
academic or research papers that you've
mentioned in the show notes.
So, Jonathan Ellis, thank you very much
for talking to Software Engineering
Radio.
Thanks for having me on the program.
Thanks for listening to Software
Engineering Radio. SE Radio is an
educational program brought to you by
Hillside Europe. If you want more
information about the podcast and the
other episodes, visit our website at
se-radio.net.
If you want to support us, you can
donate to the SE Radio team via the
website, or you can advertise for SE
Radio, for example, by clicking on the
Digg, Reddit, Delicious, and Slashdot
buttons, or by talking about us on
Twitter and Facebook. You can also
support us by joining the team and
shouldering some of the work.
To contact the team, please send an
email to team@se-radio.net,
or if your feedback is specific to an
episode, please use the comments
facility on the website so other people
can react to your comments.
This episode of SE Radio, as well as all
other episodes, are licensed under a
Creative Commons 2.5 license. Please see
the website for details.